foreign
[Music]
start with four positive real numbers a
b x and y and assume a is less than or
equal to B and X is less than y create a
right triangle with legs of length A and
B and let's assume this angle in the
upper left is Alpha
first create a scaled copy of the right
triangle where the scale value is y
then create a rotated and scaled copy of
the triangle where the scale value is X
we see that the angle Alpha appears in
these two locations in the scaled
triangles connecting the other two
vertices of the triangle together like
this creates a right triangle due to the
Pythagorean theorem the legs of this
right triangle are x times the square
root of a squared plus b squared and Y
times the square root of a squared plus
b squared and let's label the angle in
the upper left beta finally we can
create a rectangular diagram from this
trapezoid by adding this right triangle
with legs of length b y minus ax and a y
plus b x the bottom angle in this
triangle must be Alpha plus beta by
construction because it's complementary
to the other acute angle which is
complementary to Alpha plus beta
now we can get an interesting formula by
Computing Alpha plus beta in two ways
first of all it's the arc tangent of a y
plus BX divided by b y minus ax
according to the upper right triangle on
the other hand Alpha is the arctangent
of a y divided by b y according to the
left triangle and beta is the arc
tangent of x times the square root of a
squared plus b squared divided by y
times the square root of a squared plus
b squared according to the inner
triangle notice that we can cancel the
Y's and cancel the square root of a
squared plus b squareds and we end up
with the formula that arc tangent of A
over B plus the arc tangent of X over Y
is equal to the arctangent of a y plus
BX divided by b y minus ax setting both
A over B and X over y to one-fifth in
this equation yields that 2 times the
arctangent of a fifth is equal to the
arctangent of 5 12. setting both A over
B and X over y to 5 12 reveals that 2
times the arctangent of 5 12 is equal to
the arc tangent of 120 over 119 and
finally setting A over B equal to one
over one and X over y equal to 1 over
239 we get the at pi over 4 plus the arc
tangent of 1 over 239 is equal to the
arc tangent of 120 divided by 119. now
let's string these three equations
together use the second equation to
replace arctangent 120 over 119 by 2
times arctangent 5 12. then replace
arctangent 5 12 by 2 times the
arctangent of one-fifth using the first
equation if we rearrange the resulting
formula we get that pi over 4 is equal
to 4 times the arctangent of one-fifth
minus the arc tangent of 1 over 239 this
is called the matron formula and is
attributed to John Machin who discovered
it in 1706 when he used it to compute pi
to 100 decimal places
here are the first 100 decimal places
that Machin would have found
in 1873 William Shanks used the same
formula but this time got 707 digits of
pi as listed here
he was so close but in 1946 an error was
found in his work in the 528th digit
shown here
how many digits of pi do you think
modern computers can compute using this
formula leave a comment let me know